hey folks welcome back to the Dark Horse
podcast livestream Q&A session we are
going to address your super chat
questions from the first livestream and
pick up some from the second livestream
we've got a lot so we should probably
just get to it let's get to it
Oh Zack has asked me to mention to you
that there was some delay for some
people watching the initial live stream
and not for others this is confusing to
us it makes us think this is certainly
on youtubes end which is what we saw
during our early live streams when their
servers were being hit particularly hard
we don't know why we are facing that
again but you might try refreshing your
stream if you are facing some kind of
delay we do not seem to have control of
it on this end all right all right so we
are asked to Stanford study has created
a buzz cleaning we've overestimated
kovat lethality so we did in fact to
talk about this and we alluded to this
at the very beginning of this live
stream or the one that just ended and I
think we talked about this is number two
I think we talked about it in number
eight so that's where you'll find a
discussion at some length of the
Stanford study from Santa Clara County
for seroprevalence next question is also
not a question but appreciation thank
you I love the podcast and want to
support the types of inform dialogues
you are having without the censorship
filters of what eric weinstein refers to
as disk disk standing for the
distributed information suppression
complex oppression complex yes well we
appreciate it and I know Eric does as
well indeed I the Dan writes
I can smell cigarette smoke for my
neighbor's fifty feet away does that
mean I who contract coronavirus outdoors
from people fifty feet away should I
wear a face mask outdoors so I always
feel like we should just repeat that we
are not in fact medical doctors and we
can't be offering actual medical advice
for fear of people
feeling that we were responsible for
things that happened that was a result
we are not medical doctors either
indoors or outdoors yeah in neither
place in fact or in between on the
transom I think that it is possible yes
that you could contract coronavirus from
people 50 feet away outside I think it
is such a tiny possibility both because
you are outside because you are so far
away from them that for me personally I
don't wear this mask
when I'm outside I put one on as I
approach a grocery store which is pretty
much the only place I go inside that's
not our house at this point and take it
off once I'm good and free and clear of
the store or the Argus hardware stores
as well but it is possible we we now
have some evidence that it is both
airborne and aerosolized sometimes and
depending on wind and such could you
maybe under just the right which is to
say just the wrong conditions get it
that way
yes but as I think we talked about in
the last livestream study out of cases
in China found that if memory serves
something like over 7,000 cases that
they looked at they only found one or
two which had been transmitted outside
all of the rest of them were inside
mostly within homes and also within
things like health care settings and
stores nursing homes so I would just add
that there is some mystery about this it
there's lots of reason that it might be
less transmissible outdoors for example
UV light but the seemingly discontinuous
nature of outside is a bit surprising
what do you mean by this seemingly
discontinuous nature of outside the fact
that this is various levels of
transmissible indoors and there seems to
be something magical about having simply
stepped outside so a couple of things
here I want to put some hypotheses on
the table I don't necessarily believe
them to be correct but we need to figure
out what this might be it's certainly
true that the outdoor environment
involves a much larger volume of air and
so this could be a matter of diffusion
that the density of these things becomes
very low very quickly that still
wouldn't predict a zero rate but are
near zero rate but something about it it
might be an update to the dilution is
the solution to infection which doesn't
rise no one doesn't it's not a good
rhyme the other possibility is that well
there are really two possibilities I
would like to see tested one is that
this might have something to do with a
bat origin and the possibility is that
if you think about it that activity
takes place at night that means there's
not a lot of UV sanitization of the air
and bats roost in darkness at least the
bats in question roost in darkness in
these caves and so it might be that this
virus has been selected for very low
tolerance of UV light and that we are
enjoying a benefit from the fact that we
are diurnal and when we go out during
the day selected for low tolerance to UV
light because it was never exposed to it
in its original host yes and because
there are trade-offs and so therefore if
it can borrow from UV tolerance it might
pick something else somewhere else but
this predicts that it would be
transmissible outdoors at night and so
anyway I would love to see some sort of
a test and see whether there is
something that would point in that
direction
the other thing is that there are two
possibilities within the lab that could
explain this one is serial passage of
the virus through multiple generations
in the lab can result in rapid evolution
maybe in the laboratory environment
there is not very much UV light you
would expect that and so it could be the
lab environment creates a vulnerability
to the virus that isn't true of the
ancestral virus or let's see I had a
third one or it could be there's some
prior case in 1977 virus that I believe
did escape the lab and had a temperature
sensitivity that had been installed into
it I believe as a technological feature
are you quite serious uh I'm only now
learning of this it's not a coronavirus
oh so I learned about that in that
medium piece that we talked about in the
first hour but anyway all sorts of
possibilities exist my basic point would
be these are hypotheses they make
predictions and what we really need to
do is get down to work figuring out
which of these predictions are met all
right next question how does an earnest
critical thinker determine what is a
credible news source in these chaotic
times how can we determine if the
information is factual or not it's a
great question we addressed it a little
bit on the live stream which we talked
about Guayaquil the situation in
Guayaquil Ecuador is I guess its largest
city now in which you know we've we've
done a lot of talking elsewhere and
these live streams about why the
peer-reviewed literature is often not
trustworthy and so a lot of these pre
print servers and you know this is this
github document is actually providing
more accurate information but of course
the preprint servers are academic paper
or publishing academic papers and
they're highly technical so you know who
do you trust in the landscape of people
who are digesting it for you and I don't
know of a single publication that hasn't
run afoul yet right like it all of the
usual suspects really are doing some
good work and some crappy work and maybe
that's to be expected in a pandemic when
everyone is learning on the fly on the
other hand I feel like there there ought
to be it's an open niche it's an open
niche and so how does how is it how can
we determine if the information is
factual or not we talked about that some
wouldn't talk about Guayaquil you want
to add anything yeah I think the
shocking thing I mean there is a basic
test and I've forgotten what the name of
this principle is but that new sources
seem credible until they get to a
subject you know well at which point
they seem appalling which obviously
implies that their appalling on all
subjects how that happened is a little
hard to assess
but it is a conspicuous fact and having
seen every publication that I'm aware of
that is long-standing stumbled badly
suggest that you know we have an empty
niche and it's difficult to understand
why it would remain empty indeed so
probably some of you can hear that we've
we've got birds and it's a it's been to
be a problem but I think we're gonna
leave the windows open for now are where
are we what is your opinion if any on
the exhale of group mtDNA molecular
mitochondrial DNA and what the bearers
uterus be what is historically referred
to as the Holy Grail asking for a friend
thank you
I don't we did see this question before
we didn't just rank these we looked
briefly at them and neither of us can
completely make sense of what the
question means I'm afraid so
mitochondrial DNA is DNA that is only in
the mitochondria and because sperm
doesn't have mitochondria you get it
only from your mother and so you can use
mitochondrial DNA to track maternal
lineages to track female lineages
without in any any any of the messiness
of sex which the nuclear DNA has and the
X haplogroup is one particular group of
mitochondrial DNA that is found in low
percentage but I think it's it's some
Europeans North Americans but not South
Americans interestingly and maybe a few
Africans and Asian's as well but beyond
that I'm not sure what to make of the
question I mean yeah it's a sort of a
presumably the writer of the question
knows all of that and I'm not sure what
else to just say so far it looks like a
confusing pattern if you want to be more
specific at some point and point us to a
direction that you think is implied and
I'd certainly be curious are there
examples from evolution which we can
apply to our economics for instance they
both seem to prioritize short term
success at high inefficiency costs are
there any long term evolutionary
strategies it's a good question
economics really is a special case of
evolution it's a landscape like any
other except that effectively the
parameters have been reduced to really
one and there is a conflict between
short and long term profit which results
in the bias you're talking about of
course there are long term strategies
how they are discovered and then but
wrist against destruction in the short
term is it is a better question to ask
in an evolutionary a classically
biological evolutionary landscape and in
some sense the economic landscapes have
not provided a hospitable environment to
discover those strategies which is part
of what we are facing another gratitude
Brett and Heather thank you for
everything you're doing to educate
people about this and about matters
related to freedom of speech you both
inspire me to work hard on my own thesis
in psychology thank you next question
should the corruption of who the World
Health Organization be dealt with right
now even in the middle of a health
crisis I would say that pulling all
funding for the WHO from one of its
major contributors is almost certainly
going to make the problem worse should
the corruption of who be dealt with in
any way it should be acknowledged and
potentially things put in place to
suggest that there's gonna be a full
investigation later but but this
apparently retributive move by Trump
seems counterproductive at best
yeah dealt with by whom is the problem I
don't see the authority that I trust to
come in there and triage the who which
yeah it's a damned if you do damned if
you don't situation and the lesson is
how do we make sure this never happens
again all right I don't know that we can
fix it now but how do we make sure it
never happens again yeah last week you
Bret briefly distinguish between formal
Liberty and realized Liberty and said
that we should only seek to maximize the
latter can you explain sure there is a
tendency to want to provide greater
Liberty to people but how liberated you
are has a lot to do with what
opportunities you actually have
access to for so for example I have the
freedom to start an oil company if I
would like to that freedom isn't worth
very much to me because I'm in no
position to start an oil company in fact
if you told me that you would trade my
freedom to start an oil company for the
equivalent of the price of a cup of
coffee I should probably take the cup of
coffee because at least that's worth
something to me so it's a kind of
liberty but of no value realized liberty
would be those things you are actually
free to act on and my point would be if
we love Liberty we should be interested
in increasing realize Liberty not
abstract theoretical Liberty next
question is the extreme use of soap and
hand sanitizers leaving us vulnerable to
other diseases and weakening our immune
systems long term well we need to
embrace germs after this is over to a
certain extent yeah I think you know
we've we've discussed this a couple of
other times and in some of their cue
cues and a user names potentially at
least it is leaving us vulnerable to two
bacteria it's not clear the extent of
that vulnerability but just as the
hygiene hypothesis for which there was
much supporting evidence suggests that -
growing up in too clean a home leaves
children with immune systems that are
hyper responsive and thus with children
and then adults who tend to have higher
rates of allergies we might expect that
over cleaning our environments are going
to either get rid of some of our
microbiota that we need or leave us with
immune systems that don't know how to
properly react
I think the category is to broaden
there's a difference between soap which
just mechanically takes let's say
something that is covered in lipid and
allows water to strip it from your hands
which is unlikely to select in favor of
some kind of increased insidiousness or
vulnerability on the part of the person
washing their hands and an antibacterial
soap that functions like an antibiotic
where it's a continuous selective
environment so physical removal
of stuff with soap is probably pretty
safe
likewise things like alcohol that kill
viruses without likely selecting for a
high durability these things are
probably relatively safe the other thing
is we live in an environment that isn't
natural to us so we have a great many
more pathogens there may not be a good
answer if you lived in your ancestral
environment encountering at least a
large fraction of the bacteria that are
in that environment might be unavoidable
and it might result in proper immunity
but you're now exposed to whatever
everybody else on the train has when you
get on the train car that's a that's a
very dangerous situation so I think we
need to rethink the problem rather than
imagine there's a simple solution to it
yeah there won't be a simple solution
but it's also true that we are
multitudes right that we include the
microbe I we have a microbiome right in
our in our gut in our skin that we have
no idea of even twenty years ago and
certainly fifty years ago so imagining
that we are only the DNA that is inside
the nuclei and the mitochondria of
ourselves is not right so we are reliant
on this interactive community of other
organisms and so stripping them away
with some regularity may well have that
effects yes definitely don't eat soap
and hand sanitizer and that would be
that would be bad and no that was not a
trump reference really no I wasn't I
never mind
in February South China Agricultural
University wrote a paper claiming they
had a Pangolin SAR scope to RNA sequence
matching with greater than 99%
specificity but they refused to release
the whole sequence and now everything
has to be deleted question mark question
mark so that seems like a claim that we
can't assess I don't I don't know if
that's true or not yep it would
certainly be interesting if it was true
but who's to say and and who exactly has
an interest in not blaming pangolins
here how does the OEM what did you think
might mean Ridge '''l equipment
that is the original equipment
manufacturer of a kovat antibody test
figure out the accuracy how would they
find subjects they a hundred percent now
never had the virus without having a
standard test in the first place
well they presumably there's blood
there's blood in the blood supply that
predates when the virus emerged is is
the obvious way to do this and I believe
in fact even as flawed as that Santa
Clara County paper was I believe that's
part of how they were establishing their
imagined accuracy rates for the false
positives and false negatives is looking
at blood that had been banked before
there's any evidence that this virus had
ever come into contact with humans so on
the negative side blood that couldn't
possibly have been infected and on the
positive side you could do an assay in
which you actually isolated the virus
itself from the patient yep in some
species of two questions from echo in
some species it's most of the older
males offspring that lives on through
dominance and fantasy and other
strategies is it a group strategy for
the species to select for longer
lifespan is it a group is a troubling
word here depends if you mean that in
the narrow sense or the broad sense is a
group strategy for the species to select
for longer lifespan individually longer
lifespan no not inherently lifespan is
effectively a means to an evolutionary
end and we have been selected for longer
lifespans than our close relatives on
earth because presumably that served the
interests of our lineages but it is not
inherently so rapid turnover can be a
strategy long lifespan can be a strategy
they respond to different selective
regimes yeah and so I mean there are
there are as is alluded to here many
species in which you have territorial
males the dominant ones tend to be older
males until suddenly they are not
dominant anymore but you have an
increase in dominance and therefore
presumably an increase in RS and
reproductive success that correlates
with dominance and therefore correlates
with age and you might imagine
that it's the youngest but highly
fertile females who are the most
dominant in species that have female
dominance but it's not always the case
so in some boy I'm trying to think is it
hyenas and some species of primates in
which dominance is actually also
increases with age which is strange
because reproductive capability
decreases somewhat with age and then
dominance is inherited by the daughters
either in oldest to youngest our
youngest to oldest so there's all sorts
of different different models of how
dominance works and is inherited usually
with insects typically you don't end up
with dominance other than in humans
being inherited between sexes so I think
Brett you did a pretty good job with the
rest part of that second part of the
question is the story of Abraham the
story of human populations selecting for
longer life span through encouraging
mating with old males is God as a
bearded old man
Geron to philia propaganda oh yeah geez
I don't know how to how to address that
I don't know how to address it seriously
frankly those stories could be a lot of
different things they could be the
self-interest of people who had
influence over those stories being
written they could be adaptive content
in some way we don't understand it's
certainly worth thinking about but I
don't I don't know the answer offhand
yeah I mean across across pre-industrial
human cultures in humans dominance does
correlate with age and men and the kind
of power that is wielded culturally
increases with age and the and therefore
and that's correlated with with sexual
power to a large degree whereas sexual
power and women obviously decreases with
age and other kinds of power can
increase but you have different moments
in the lifespan when there is there is
power residing primarily in each of the
sexes which has a lot to do with the way
wealth does or doesn't accumulate
yeah exactly from Holley math nerd what
is the evolution evolutionary mechanism
behind phantom pain is it different
phenomenon and missing or amputated
limbs versus other experiences of
phantom pain I would argue that what you
have is a contingency program built-in
that is getting misfired in a
circumstance that probably isn't all
that common so if you think about the
the danger if you suddenly don't have
data coming in from your arm it's
possible that there's a reason for that
that should capture your attention
critically and it is also possible that
your arm was carefully removed by a
surgeon and that the your attention
being called to it isn't in your
interest it would be nice to just shut
down that data but you've got a
comparison between basically false
positives and false negatives and that's
good experiencing pain from a limb you
no longer have may be the result of a
program that makes you think in the
absence of data worried that you may be
doing damage yeah tend to this tend to
this tend to this so that it doesn't get
infected so that you don't and you know
in the pre surgical era mostly it
wouldn't be a so you don't lose your arm
it would be so if so you don't lose your
life ya proposition yeah and so also
that you know the tingling of limbs is
obviously a different phenomenon but it
would be the same kind of thing where
you you know cut off circulation to a
limb or you end up blocking nerve
impulses and it's just kind of an it
this so uncomfortable an emergency
signal that you will take action and my
guess is phantom pain is a bias towards
action that works against you yeah okay
live at your own risk which is something
that Brett said in the last live stream
I believe live at your own risk
seems to be short distance away from
being a reason to end the lockdown do
you see a bright line between opening
beaches and parks and reopening society
more generally I don't see a bright line
I see a bright line we were talking
about it before okay
beaches and parks are outdoors we have
reason to think but
so opening society more generally is a
continuum itself that's that's why I see
no bright line that there are there are
a number of ways of opening in fact
we've already
I think talked about maybe not we
haven't talked about here but here in
Oregon the governor is talking about
allowing non-essential medical and
dental procedures to resume maybe as
early as May 1st that is not allowing
bars to reopen so there is there is a
bright line on thresholds on transoms
right between indoors and outdoors but
there are also a number of other things
that can start reopening before you say
it's a free-for-all again yeah I would
say we should be very cautious about the
urge to reopen you know we are feeling a
kind of pain from what we no longer have
access to and so that pressure is
automatic there will also be different
levels of hazard in different places but
as I keep saying I fear the way the game
theory will unfold as some people have
liberties restored to them that other
people don't we need to think very
carefully about how not to trigger race
to the bottom scenario which i think is
highly likely yeah and I guess one more
thing I would say in response to this is
that live at your own risk which I
really enjoyed as a sentence when you
said it really applies to the individual
and the lockdown is a population level
analysis and the distinction between
individual and population level analyses
is one that is maybe the most widely
missed in analyses of what this is and
you know I think it's the big error of
libertarians forget right that it
misunderstands there are there are
problems that cannot be solved by
everyone simply acting in ways that
allows them to have the maximum freedom
personal responsibility will result in
an epidemiological catastrophe so live
at your own risk was not intended as a
defense of some kind of broadly and
simply applied libertarianism what it
was is a response to the learned
helplessness that comes when too much
action is taken to protect you from each
and every thing where you think the
beach is only open a bowl if the
our lifeguards on duty the fact is
somehow there are no lifeguards on duty
at night and we don't have massive
numbers of drownings does it happen two
people drown they do but in general
they're behaving stupidly and the key
thing to understand is maybe there's a
difference in how you should behave if
there's a lifeguard there to save you or
maybe there isn't that much difference
than the lifeguard is really when things
have gone very very wrong kind of a last
yeah lifeguard shouldn't be Plan B it
doesn't yeah I've got should be plan Zed
it should be plan Zed so you know can
you go to the beach if there's no
lifeguard on duty yeah you should be
able to go to the beach if the
lifeguards on duty and frankly you
should have the wisdom to know how to
view your safety in a place where
government can't take care of you good
it's a question about whether or not
we've seen a particular article in the
Houston Chronicle which we haven't but
it is apparently about the link between
Cove at 19 and strokes and this is
something we didn't get to in the first
in the first hour of today's livestream
but yeah on April 17th science published
a news article suggesting that blood
clots were perhaps a major predictor of
mechanism of harm in Kovan 19 and then
on April 25th that's today
WAPA The Washington Post published an
article which you would sent to me on
you know we just had healthy young
people you know thirties forties early
fifties young ish young and youngish
people with no underlying health
conditions experiencing strokes a rather
unnerving rate and also I think in the
same article maybe there was a
suggestion that there were a whole lot
more deaths from stroke maybe in New
York City I mean I may have the
information wrong here but for which we
will never know if they were koban 19
related because autopsies weren't being
done because the morgues are otherwise
involved at this point yeah so there's
there's possibly quite a strong
suggestion of mechanism of blood clots
here of strokes as being a risk for
even young healthy people and once again
we are perhaps never going to have the
entire story because some of the
information is already being lost yeah
although it would seem that awareness
now might cause us to be able to to test
new cases I think it was also striking
not only were young people getting
strokes but they were getting strokes
that were characteristic of old people
yeah that's right
so anyway yes it's conspicuous and does
suggest something 30 minutes we're gonna
try to get through just a couple more of
these apologies we're gonna and then we
will we will switch over to it okay have
we run into any papers surfacing on the
potential neurological impacts yeah
boy it's terrifying and I don't know
what more we should say about that now
we'll probably come back to it another
live stream not just respiratory but
cardiac neurological basically every
system seems to be potentially affected
here so this actually is touched on in
the medium post that we pointed to in
the first half of this live stream and
I've seen it in a couple other places
and what seems to be emerging is at
least some of the neurological
connection for Kovan 19 is the result of
a bad interaction with herpes viruses
which reside inside of neurons and I
believe the medium post suggests that
the possibility for SARS Cove 2 to enter
neurons may be the result of a novel
protease insertion which is one of the
places in which it is in which this
virus seems to throw a challenge to us
phylogenetically so a unit that
shouldn't be in the genome based on what
it's related to that seems to be that
maybe facilitating transition into
neurons which has then also been
connected by others to the symptom that
some people get where they lose the
sense of smell and taste all of a sudden
maybe due to inflammation
in the central nervous system okay we're
just gonna do two more in this super
chat and switch to the other one
apologies for the question many
questions that we've missed
what is are your opinions about the
possibility of runaway global heating
producing a scorched earth and
extinction of most of life currently
here hard to say
I do think climate change is a very
severe danger even in a case where it is
relatively if we choose amongst as I've
said elsewhere many many times I am NOT
a fan of these highly complex models
that imagine they can predict what the
future of planet Earth looks like I
believe that the proper use of models is
to generate hypotheses which can then be
tested against actual data so I don't
like spooking ourselves with models on
the other hand one of the things that
people I think fail to appreciate is
that even minor amounts of climate
change are likely to be very
destabilizing politically and the system
that they are connected to is so fragile
that as we've seen with SARS Cove - we
have a collapse of many global systems
as a result of what is actually if you
think about the large numbers of
asymptomatic cases a small perturbation
you know it has created a massive
economic hazard so that is the kind of
linkage that can take a manageable
catastrophe at the level of climate and
turn it into an unmanageable catastrophe
at the level of conflict warfare refugee
crises those sorts of things so beware
the linkages and I do think this ought
to be a a matter of major and immediate
concern for us irrespective of which of
the models is most predictive I agree
one last question from this Washington
native love you guys thank you do you
believe that the idea that religions or
religious traditions have nothing to
offer us is ironically itself a mind
virus maladaptive to human behavior
Thanks so I like this question yes in
short yes I have said so in fact I
I have said that religion can't be a
mind virus but New Atheism can be and so
yes I think clearly these things have
served the populations that believed in
them served doesn't make them good it
doesn't mean that the ways that those
populations were served were morally
defensible they in some cases are and in
some cases aren't but have they been
adaptive no question or there should be
no question logically
it cannot really be otherwise that's
right
forty-two thank you okay forty-two the
last one forty-three all right here we
go this is to me h/h read your bio I'm
trying to figure out which bio is been
read here so read your bio regarding
Squirrel cuckoos and tanagers I must
have something on my website about
Squirrel cuckoos and Terriers which are
two of my favorite well squirrel cuckoo
is a particular species of bird near
travel apparent Andrus is a clade of
just gloriously colored and birds from
the Neotropics it's the dry season now
in the matagalpa highland jungle of
nicaragua yesterday a rare squirrel
cuckoo and the first scarlet tanager
sighting bird bath is only water now at
our mill Epona bee sanctuary well you
have made me want to be and they mighta
Kalpa highland jungle of nicaragua at
the moment thank you for that there's no
question there and I think I won't just
start talking about squirrel cuckoos and
tanagers because I'd never stopped thank
you brett has Eric been watching you and
Heather since the lockdown if so what
has been some of his feedback I don't
know you'd have to ask you'd have to ask
Eric okay how can an RN protect their
family while returning home from caring
for a Kovac patient oh boy yeah that's
tough in part boy early on maybe even
before we began doing these live streams
we read an analysis that suggested maybe
in Europe already
health care workers were being provided
places to go such that they did not have
to go home and and even people who've
just tested positive should not have to
go home I mean this this is the go-to
strategy at the moment because because
hospitals either are or a risk of being
overrun but we know that within
household transmission is one of the
major ways that this disease is
spreading so best if you don't have to
go home but if you do have to go home
and you have anyway to self isolate
within the home that's the thing to do
try to sleep separately try to use a
separate bathroom trying to cook for
your family probably anything else well
I you know I'm thinking longer term here
and I think one of the things about this
crisis is that it is revealing all of
the things that we should have done and
didn't and you know I've also been
looking at objects and thinking what we
have mispriced based on not
understanding how they would be valued
under this circumstance you know
mother-in-law Welling a chest freezer we
we sold to our neighbors when we left
Olympic unit s freezer we sold a an
Airstream trailer of a certain size that
you could Park in your driveway and if
you came home from doing medical care
you could stay and so anyway none of
that is useful advice for somebody on
the front lines at the moment all I can
say is try to self isolate hand wash
wear mask even indoors that sort of
thing but you know we're with you it's
not a good situation and we are not
happy that civilization has left you in
the in the bind you're in yeah
what do you think what do you think
about the low cupboard numbers out of
India lack of testing question mark
thank you for your invaluable work
during these Corin times it's a good
word boy there's I I feel like there is
something going on in India and I don't
think it's just about like
testing and I can't remember what I
think the story might be have you seen
anything I don't have it in my head at
the moment no but the variance on levels
of testing is so high that at least we
got to falsify that as the driver before
we start trying to explain it as a
phenomenon it needs to at least be a
phenomenon before we try to explain what
sort of phenomenon it is yeah I'm gonna
I'm gonna try to remember I thought I
saw something online about India that
suggested that it maybe wasn't at least
just about the lack of testing but gonna
try to look into that for next time
idea oh this is from Austin hello Austin
this one of our friends and former
students general descent your
grandchildren are you men literally
reappear and their sons sons and women
and their daughters daughters etc
thoughts it's a good metaphor for how to
take care of future generations in a way
that evolutionarily we would be built to
do if our ancestors had had as much
power to harm future generations as we
do so elsewhere I will make an argument
about the distortion of self and I think
Austin here is pointing to a correction
for it that is useful good hi from
Portugal considering the cost of
offspring and your deep understanding of
evolution why did you have children we
are asked with Zach in the room weren't
there cheaper ways to get tech
assistance during a pandemic sorry love
to you all including Zach yeah this is a
hard question to answer
eh I hear a lot of people talking about
I don't want to have kids because I
don't want to bring kids into a world
like this which i think is actually a
bit upside down right I was born into a
world like this I'm not sorry I'm here
you know I do realize we're all in right
this is potentially going to go
is there a polite synonym for tits-up
now at some point it might go tits up
but
I'm not sorry I'm here the worst that
can happen is I can lose the gift of
life that I was given
okay well that's coming anyway so why
would my kids feel any differently all
right my kids our kids we have been very
honest with them about the peril of the
world they've been born into the
parallel this particular moment all of
those things they're not depressed they
are happy insightful good people they're
exactly the kind of people you want on
planet earth so I don't find it
compelling that the world is screwed up
therefore you shouldn't bring more
people into it now if you don't feel
compelled to raise children and you
don't feel maybe that you are in a
position to do it well don't let me or
anyone else push you into doing it but
to the extent that humanity will either
go on or it won't go on bring the kids
into the world that you feel that you
ought to have and raise them as well as
possible wonderful
this next question has some acronyms in
it that I am not familiar with does your
rodent work on telomeres Brett have
implications for crl populations of
rabbit mini pig sheep and pig histo and
taco studies typically required for
preclinical submissions for IND and IDE
approvals from the FDA all right FDA
I've got yeah ever yeah you got all
right off the top of my head the the
argument I made in that paper was that
this problem of breeding mice in a
laboratory environment creating an
elongation of their telomeres which then
distorts their longevity and risk of
cancer that hazard will happen any time
you breed small animals in an
environment where you're trying to
maximize the return on your investment
so that is to say any time you're trying
to get the maximum number of mice from
the minimum amount of mouths chow you
will end up making the same error where
you breed young animals and in small
creatures breeding young animals will
cause this effect and I believe
it has been seen in chickens it's been
seen in Asian hamsters it's been seen in
rats it's been seen in mice I don't know
if it's been seen in anything else but
at some point an animal is large enough
that when you elongate its telomeres in
this fashion it doesn't survive to
reproduce so it's not a viable mechanism
I think pigs are likely too large to see
this affect so below a certain size you
will see it above a certain size you
probably won't so the next question
probably responsive to the previous one
is are mini pigs real there are no more
real than birds on invasive species in
your opinion are humans part of nature I
hope a full discussion on the top on
this topic one day outside of the desk
because desk yeah of course we are we
have spread across the planet more fully
and more widely than any other species
and it's interesting to compare us to
some of the other generalists mountain
lions do a pretty good job most of
that's without our help
explicitly most of the other really
widespread species have done so with our
help
things like pigeons and their Norway rat
and a few cockroach species but yeah we
should we should probably talk
explicitly about invasive species at
some length another time sure how are we
doing on time Zak okay good
why is UV light via in death endoscopy
not being taken seriously as a treatment
at specific wavelengths it's been shown
to be safe on skin and effective on
virus yeah I don't know this is one of
these things where until it is
investigated we don't know how well it
works but this was apparently a cure
that was being advanced for a time and
apparently it was extremely useful and
then was it closed
for I can't remember no no not if a
corona virus it was in the context I
believe maybe a polio but anyway
basically sanitizing the blood either by
circulating it out of the body through
some UV or putting
kind of a light in the circulatory
pathway apparently was effective for
some things and then was almost
immediately eclipsed by some alternative
therapy that became the standard anyway
I'll look into it see if we can't find a
link for the next live stream well the
cynic in me suspects that UV light is
impossible to patent and the replacement
was drug therapy but but I don't know
this I have seen another story you're
talking about
news accuracy gell-mann amnesia effect
yeah that is the answer to the question
of what what the name of the effect that
you were referencing earlier yes thank
you for that considerable donation from
Jim Frey for another chest freezer
thank you for that unfortunately the
problem at the moment is they're not
available seriously do it do a search
like you went looking early on at Home
Depot and Lowe's and we're finding them
out of stock and just yesterday the day
before I was looking and they're all
back or as far as I can tell through
July so there are a lot of people out
there trying to get some stuff in
storage before possible breaks in the
supply chain to things like beef and
pork for instance so huh right well why
is my grandpa tall and his ugly feet
meanwhile I have cute feet and I am
short well maybe he's not your grandpa
that's a possibility yes I hope no but
seriously
your grandpa is on average 25% related
to you because you get half of each of
your parents DNA into 50% related to
each of your parents and they in turn
got 50% of their DNA from each of their
parents and you multiply those halves to
get one-quarter average relatedness to
each of your grandparents and similarly
to each of your grandchildren which
presumably you don't have yet but that
doesn't mean that you're exactly 25% so
this is this is only one kind of way to
answer this question of course but that
doesn't mean that you're exactly 25%
related to your grandfather you are on
average 25% related to your grandfather
or everyone is i overage 20
related their grandfathers and that can
range from zero to fifty percent which
is to say if your grandfather happened
to have passed on to his son let's see
how do we do it if if you received from
your father only that part of his genome
which came from his father which is say
your grandfather then you would be 50%
related to your your grandfather exactly
the same degree that your father's
related to him but the chances of that
happening are very low and similarly if
your father receipt passed on to you
only that part of his genome that he got
from his mother then he would be 0%
related a genetic level to your
grandfather so goes from zero to 50% 25%
and basically your your cute feet which
we're gonna remain agnostic about and
are you know potentially just you didn't
get your grandfather's feet alleles and
then of course height is this continuous
variable which is informed by so much
besides genetics it's in it's informed
by early developmental experience and
and food especially yeah I would also
just point out in my case my brother and
I are full siblings and we are miles
apart in height his height being
anomalous in the family and what's more
we know that the story my mother tells
of us being full siblings is true
because Eric and I share a rare
colorblindness so we see color alike and
like nobody else we know so anyway all I
would say is that these parameters are
complex what group of alleles you get
coupled with the environment that you're
raised in has big impacts on what your
phenotype ends up being and so you can
be wildly off of somebody you're closely
related to for many reasons if we are
living in a simulation why have a child
we're not living in a simulation well I
don't know which we they're referring to
they may be living in a simulation we
are not living in a semi
and so that's why we had kids right
there you go okay so we have just a
couple minutes left I think zach is that
right with ten minutes okay so we're
going to answer one or two more from the
previous Super chat Joe Rogan insists
that taking high-dose vitamin C and D
boost immunity on his podcast constantly
not correcting a deficiency has in this
been debunked
for instance the Linus Pauling debacle
in the 70s all right what I don't know
is how we know that we are not
correcting for deficiency in other words
deficiency could mean a lot of things
high dose of I do I mean I guess
presumably what the question means is
that doses that are so high that you
would have corrected for any deficiency
early on in the protocol would still
have a positive effect but nonetheless a
lot depends on what a deficiency might
look like one thing that a deficiency
might look like for vitamin D is that
the the advice the widespread advice to
slather yourself from head to toe with
sunscreen every time you leave the house
that has been prominent in at least
America for gosh decades at this point
has probably led to widespread vitamin D
deficiency the idea that Sun is actually
both good for you in some doses and
important was considered anathema in
medical circles and and still is in many
I would say so you know needing vitamin
D and not being able to get it from the
source that you you should be getting it
from may have left many people with
considerable deficiencies so your
argument here as I hear it is you're not
compelled out there that it's not
correcting a deficiency
yeah I'm not I want to see the protocol
that demonstrates that it boosts
immunity that so basically this is sorry
but this is harking back to something we
talked about one of the last couple
times where you have boosting immunity
beyond something that is normally that
raises the question of why why then if
the immune system could do that isn't it
normally
what kinds of trade-offs are being
invoked whereas if there's some sort of
threshold line that the immune system
should be set at and we are constantly
many of us are constantly effectively
ill enough from some effects like not
getting enough sunlight such as we are
below that line we are not trying to
boost beyond what is normally selected
for it but just get back to baseline
especially if in order to source high
amounts of vitamin C you have to go
outside and so you get a compensation
for vitamin D that you were lacking yeah
I I don't know it's also possible that
there's some sort of an extreme file
effect vitamin C is water-soluble one of
the reasons it's safe to take large
amounts of vitamin C is that your body
has a very easy time flushing it so it's
possible that introducing a bunch of
vitamin C does something like changes pH
and it functions in an analogous way to
a fever a fever takes a pathogen that is
evolved to parasitize an individual who
has a particular native temperature and
it alters the temperature on them
putting in an environment they're not
adapted to so it's possible that
introducing large amounts of vitamin C
might simply give a challenge to
pathogens that were working to infect
you that they would find inhospitable
but that's very different when we say
immunity we're actually talking about a
category of cells that has particular
kinds of activity so you know is vitamin
C for example acting prior to any
immunity and looking like it boosts
immunity by virtue of the fact that you
get less sick or get sick less often
this is it actually tied in to the
immune system in some way yeah which
I've never heard that second thing you
know I've heard a lot of this boosts
immunity yeah but might it not you know
if Pauling was right about anything to
do with vitamin C actually being one of
the things that we don't have enough of
in our diets you know in a class of
things called antioxidants
is it possible that vitamin C is only
doing that thing which is basically
scouring the human ecosystem for easy
targets to basically cleanse us of that
has absolutely nothing to do with immune
function then find yourself if you're in
an appropriate level of possession of
vitamin C in your body not getting sick
as often and so it feels like I've got
immune health and it's actually other
kinds of health not immune health what
core belief or good generally genuinely
motivates you to hope act and keep going
got something not yet yeah for me I
guess I mean this is a very it's a very
personal thing you know it's about
motivational structures and let's just
try try this imagine for a second you're
standing in a football stadium and
you're surrounded by all of the
materials that are unrecoverable that
you will use all the barrels of oil that
will be lost warming your house and
fueling your car and all that and all of
the tracks that will be thrown away and
never recovered right it's a giant mound
of stuff my feeling is it makes sense to
try to live such that that amount of
cost to the world is more than
compensated for and it's not easy to do
and most people actually I don't think
have the opportunity to do it but for
those of us who do have the opportunity
to make the world better in some way I
sort of feel like it's it's the price of
admission and anyway that motivates me I
like to do things that as far as I can
tell count favorably towards my net
impact on planet Earth while I'm here
your mileage may vary that's good I
think maybe that's all right
our new super chat is would Zack be
willing to check on the video being out
of sync with the audio Zack would very
definitely be willing to check but I
know from many conversations with Zack
that this appears to be happening on
youtubes end we had it on an early
couple of live streams and we are now
seeing it again and the Cure came as
YouTube altered something why we're
seeing it again
we have no idea it could be the time of
day not sure but anyway we apologize for
it we will continue to do as much
troubleshooting as possible but this
appears to be downstream of us okay so
it sounds like we've got time for one or
two more questions I'm just trying to
find which ones we haven't answered yet
here from the first super chat since you
are both currently working on a book do
you have any writing advice based on
your fresh experience this is definitely
going to be highly variable by person I
know that I tend to write in bursts and
then like to go and walk so if I'm great
if I'm in nature and you know I write
for a while and then I go mmm hiking for
three miles three hours we did this in
the Amazon in January but I also then in
February when I got really sick did it
in LA and other places as well San
Antonio back in November and often in
within cities I'll go between coffee
shops and you know write for a while and
then just walk and walk and walk and
find others off eShop and have some more
cappuccino and and write again that's
you know one of many many ways to answer
the question but it's one that's one
truth I'm coming to the conclusion that
writing is best done after digging you
dig a hole you throw all of your
connections to the Internet into it you
fill it in and then you can go write
maybe with a typewriter or something
like that but somehow the Internet is a
major obstacle to getting things done
that one needs to get
for me all right let's see apologies
guys yeah
[Music]
Iceland apparently had 790 positive 1570
recovered 10 deaths very low death rate
I apologies guys I'm just having a hard
time finding reading these questions are
there any experimental peptides drugs
experiments with any degree of success
with telomere integrity I see lots of
research online your thoughts please
yeah I don't think telomere integrity is
it's the wrong model it's as if people
imagine that your telomeres are fraying
like the Aglets on your shoelaces but
that's not what's going on the telomeres
are eroding and that is an adaptation
the loss of telomere is protecting you
from runaway cell lines and the way we
know this is the telomere integrity was
maintained consistently in our first
ancestors that had telomeres so we are
complex eukaryotes linear chromosomes
that's where telomeres show up but the
first eukaryotes were colonial
single-celled creatures reactions first
ones weren't colonial at all but quickly
thereafter you have things like yeast
right so yeast has linear chromosomes
they have telomeres on their ends and
those telomeres are maintained at a
given length because there's no such
thing as cancer in a yeast cancer is
growth and growth is positive and so
what I'm telling you is that shortening
telomeres evolved after the magic for
keeping them from shortening had already
been discovered by selection that tells
us that the fact of them shortening is
not because selection hasn't figured out
how to protect them it's because they're
shortening is valuable and the reason
that it's valuable
I believe is the one that I argued in
the paper that has now gotten some
attention which is that they're
shortening protects you from cell lines
that have escaped and would grow into a
tumor that would crowd out some vital
organ and kill you so in some sense you
should be grateful for the fact that
they're shortening and you should be
more accepting of its downside which is
that you will grow feeble with age so at
some level the very terminology telomere
integrity misses the point that there is
a trade-off it assumes that there's only
one direction to be to be pursuing and
of course the cancer researcher the
anti-cancer researchers and the
anti-aging researchers if they use a
term like telomere integrity would see
it in opposite directions yeah and even
more so I believe the question
referenced the thing as he sees on the
Internet
where people are trying to sell you
stuff and the idea that you are
degrading because of some flaw in your
molecular makeup that can be
counteracted by some simple other set of
molecules that's a very nice story it
just not true yeah all right okay well
that was great we will see you all next
time we appreciate your support please
like subscribe notify and spread the
word we'll be back on Tuesday at 3:30
Pacific time alright stay safe